Guide to the Charles Douglas Allen Papers
Saratoga Springs Public Library
Charles Douglas Allen Papers
1930 - 1945
This collection depicts personal memories of Charles Douglas Allen’s life, family and friends summarizing his WWII service, High School and college sports activities. The collection also includes religious ephemera.
1 doc box
Allen, Charles Douglas
Saratoga Springs Public Library Saratoga Room
2006.16
Items in this collection may be subject to Copyright Laws.
Charles Douglas Allen- passed away November 26, 1983 at Saratoga Hospital following a short illness. He was born in Saratoga Springs on October 26, 1924, son of Jennie Frances Biggie and James Allen. Charles attended Saratoga Springs High School 1930-1934 and played basketball throughout his attendance. He then served in the 389th Bomb Group, known in more familiar terms as "the Sky Scorpions", flew strategic bombing missions in B-24 Liberators from Hethel, England. They also sent detachments to join bases in North Africa at Benghazi No. 10, Libya. Stationed at Fort Logan, CO and reassigned to Europe with the 389th Bomber Group and presented with the distinguished unit citation 1943 August 1 “The 300 Club” completing 300th mission in European Theater of Operations. Part of the 1st bombing raid in Rome and Wiener-Neustadt and led B-24 Liberator bombers on D-Day.
Saratoga Springs (N.Y.); Denver (Colo.); Edinburgh (Scotland); England; Saratoga Springs High School; United States. Army Air Forces. Personnel Narratives Division. Combat air forces of World War II, Army of the United States.; Basketball stories; Allen, Charles Douglas; Biggie, Jennie Francis; Lombardi, Frank; Arpey,Joe; Bardino, Charles Sr.; Boys Scouts of America.
The collection is housed in a single box in folders in which include black and white photographs of Charles Douglas Allen, family, friends and military memories of WWII. Newspaper clipping with photos including James Brophy, Hayes Donohue, and John Cummings, and Letterhead for University Club Basketball Team, Douglas Allen, Manager. Local Saratoga Springs High School sports schedules and memorabilia. The order of the collection is chronological including school, religious and sports memorabilia, military and obituary notices.
- Personal Papers
- 1926, 1927 Certificates Bethesda Sunday School, 1934 Saratoga Springs High School diploma. 1934 Graduation Ball Dance card with pencil. June 1930, 1942 Recorder, Boy Scout certificate, Board of Elections Certification 1967
- Sports Ephemera
- 1930-1934 sports schedules Saratoga Springs High School. University Club Tournament tickets and local business sponsorship pamphlet. Official Saratoga UAA Invitational Basketball 1940 programs including committee ribbons.
- Photographs
- Allen, Charles Douglas and family black and white photos 1935-1958
- Military photos: 1938-1944 include B&W photos of Charles Douglas Allen barrack mates, Denver, Colorado 1942. Edinburgh Scotland, 1943-1944. 389th Bombers group and plane Allen, Charles Douglas flew in; 1942. Bases in Edinburgh Scotland, and Denver Colorado. US Army Airforce Photo 1942 November 20 Charles D Allen framed with inset print of US President Franklin D Roosevelt and General Douglas Macarthur.
- Military Ephemera
- Newspaper clippings, 389th Bomber Group reassignment. United States Army Air Forces Technical School diploma 1943 February 3. 8th Air Force Lib,389th Bombardment Group “300 Club” Missing in Action Soldier poster
- Personal Ephemera
- Charles Douglas Allen child’s prayer book, 1922; Jennie Francis Biggie prayer book, 1892; Gift prayer book from Charles best friend Joe Arpey, © 1935; Gibson Birthday card (no date); Padded American Greetings Birthday Card 1964